<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<images>
<pic>
        <image>images/xray.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of Library of Congress</copyright>
        <caption>1895 – X-rays, USA</caption>
	<desc>Thomas Edison refines the process of using X-rays using a fluoroscope. X-rays become the standard for medical exams. X-rays identify bony structures and diseases of the soft tissues.</desc> 
    </pic>

<pic>
        <image>images/roosevelt.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of Library of Congress</copyright>
        <caption>1942 – The Manhattan Project, USA</caption>
	<desc>President Roosevelt launches the Manhattan Project with the goal of developing nuclear weapons.</desc> 
    </pic>
<pic>
        <image>images/trinity.jpg</image>
		<copyright> .</copyright>
        <caption>July 16, 1945 – Trinity Test, Alamogordo, USA</caption>
	<desc>Known as the Trinity test, the first atomic bomb is detonated in New Mexico.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/hiroshima.jpg</image>
		<copyright>.</copyright>
        <caption>August 6, 1945 – Hiroshima, Japan</caption>
	<desc>In an effort to defeat Japan and bring an end to World War II, the Americans dropped a uranium bomb code named "Little Boy" on the city of Hiroshima, Japan, devastating the city and killing approximately 140 000 people.</desc> 
    </pic>
    <pic>
        <image>images/nagasaki2.jpg</image>
		<copyright>.</copyright>
        <caption>August 9, 1945 – Nagasaki, Japan</caption>
	<desc>In a final assault on Japan by the Americans in World War II, a plutonium bomb code named "Fat Man" was dropped on the city of Nagasaki, Japan, killing at least 70 000 people.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/ultrasound.jpg</image>
		<copyright>American Institute for Ultrasound in Medicine</copyright>
        <caption>Late 1940s – Ultrasound, USA</caption>
	<desc>Dr. George Ludwig developed the first ultrasound for medical use on the human body at the Naval Medical Research Institute in Maryland.  An ultrasound uses high-frequency sound waves to create images of internal organs and structures within the body.</desc> 
    </pic>
    <pic>
        <image>images/semipalatinsk.jpg</image>
		<copyright>.</copyright>
        <caption>August 29, 1949 – Semipalatinsk Test Site, Kazakhstan</caption>
	<desc>Russia detonates its first nuclear device, a plutonium bomb.</desc> 
    </pic>
 <pic>
        <image>images/nuclear1951.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of Argonne National Laboratory</copyright>
        <caption>December 2, 1951 – First Electricity Using Nuclear Power</caption>
	<desc>About 100 kW of electricity was generated in Idaho, USA.  This was the first time electricity was generated by a nuclear reactor.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/power1954.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of Argonne National Laboratory</copyright>
        <caption>June 26, 1954 – First Electricity for Power Grid, Russia</caption>
	<desc>In Obninsk, Russia, approximately 5 MW of electricity was generated to supply a power grid.  This was the first time that a nuclear reactor had been used to supply electricity to a power grid. </desc> 
    </pic>
    <pic>
        <image>images/mayak1957.jpg</image>
		<copyright>.</copyright>
        <caption>September 29, 1957 – Mayak Nuclear Facility, Russia</caption>
	<desc>Designed to manufacture and refine plutonium for nuclear weapons, the Mayak's cooling system fails, resulting in a huge explosion equivalent to 75 tonnes of TNT. Significant amounts of radiation were emitted.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/cuban_missle.jpg</image>
		<copyright>.</copyright>
        <caption>October 1962 – The Cuban Missile Crisis</caption>
	<desc>On October 15, the United States discovered a secret installation of Soviet missiles on the island of Cuba.  President Kennedy ordered a naval blockade and demanded that the Soviet Union remove all missiles.  "Nuclear catastrophe was hanging by a thread . . . and we weren't counting days or hours, but minutes." -Soviet General and Army Chief of Operations, Anatoly Gribkov</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/nnpt1968.jpg</image>
		<copyright>© PhotoDisc/Getty Images</copyright>
        <caption>1968 – The NNPT</caption>
	<desc>The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty was created in 1968 with the purpose of limiting the spread of nuclear weapons while still allowing nations to use nuclear technology for peaceful purposes.  The treaty has currently been signed by more than 180 nations.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/england1972.jpg</image>
		<copyright>© 1995-2007 AMERICAN PHYSICAL SOCIETY. Used with permission.</copyright>
        <caption>1972 – CAT Scan, England</caption>
	<desc>Computed tomography (CT), formerly known as computed axial tomography (CAT), was developed by Godfrey Hounsfield in Hayes, England.  CT scans collect X-rays that have passed through the body with an electronic detector and then use computer technology to produce a three-dimensional image of internal structures.</desc> 
    </pic>
	
	
	
	<pic>
        <image>images/three_mile.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of U.S. National Archives</copyright>
        <caption>March 28, 1979 – Three Mile Island, USA</caption>
	<desc>The nuclear power plant located in Pennsylvania undergoes a partial core meltdown.  Debate is ongoing about the casualties of the accident, but no one denies the serious economic and political backlash against nuclear power.</desc> 
    </pic>
	
	<pic>
        <image>images/mri1980.jpg</image>
		<copyright>© c_bell/iStockphoto</copyright>
        <caption>Early 1980s – MRI, USA</caption>
	<desc>Although the first MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) machine was built in 1977 by Raymond Damadian, they were already in wide use in hospitals by the early 1980s.  MRI machines use strong magnetic fields and radio waves, allowing doctors to examine the internal structures in a body without performing surgery.  MRI offers extremely clear pictures with considerable detail, allowing doctors to make diagnoses earlier.  </desc> 
    </pic>
	
	<pic>
        <image>images/chernobyl1986.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Artur Korneev, Courtesy of the U.S. Department of Energy</copyright>
        <caption>April 26, 1986 – Chernobyl Nuclear Facility, Russia</caption>
	<desc>The Chernobyl nuclear power plant meltdown sent radioactive material throughout Russia and Europe.  Since long-term health consequences from radiation exposure are not fully understood, it will be difficult to determine Chernobyl's impact.  Predictions indicate that as a result of the Chernobyl meltdown, there will be from 30 000 to 60 000 excess cancer deaths.          </desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/india1998.jpg</image>
		<copyright>© Photodisc/Getty Images</copyright>
        <caption>1998 – India and Pakistan</caption>
	<desc>As part of their arms race, the nations of India and Pakistan each detonate several nuclear bombs in an apparent show of strength to one another.</desc> 
    </pic>
	<pic>
        <image>images/korea2006.jpg</image>
		<copyright>Courtesy of China Digital </copyright>
        <caption>October 9, 2006 – North Korea</caption>
	<desc>North Korea detonates a nuclear bomb against the warnings of many other nations.</desc> 
    </pic>
</images>